Guide to the Louise Bryant Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1913-1934, Series II
  The Journals and notebooks section is made up primarily of detailed notes Bryant kept while traveling in Europe and Asia as a journalist. Most are small notebooks, while some are pages folded in half to form booklets. These notebooks and booklets contain irregularly dated entries, sometimes daily and other times at longer intervals. The majority detail Bryant's experiences during her time in Russia in 1917 and 1920, and these Russia notebooks include notes about Vladimir Lenin, Leon Trotsky, Alexandr Kerensky, Michael Kalinin, and Maria Spiridonova. Other notebooks document her trip to France during the First World War and her travels to Uzbekistan, Latvia, and Turkey. The Turkey notebook includes notes about Kemal Atatürk. Most of these journals and notebooks relate to her work as a journalist, but some, especially the Latvian journals, record personal thoughts and experiences including her mourning the death of John Reed. The notebook on the Provincetown Players contains membership and dues lists for the theater group and minutes from one of its organizational meetings.
  The small amount of material within the Speeches section mainly relates to Bryant's 1919 speaking tour of the United States in which she presented a sympathetic view of Soviet Russia. It includes copies of two speeches as well as notes on her speech "The Truth About Russia." Correspondence relevant to this speaking trip can be found in the letters from Anna Louise Strong in Series I.
  Writings by others contain drafts and manuscripts by authors other than Bryant including Eugene O'Neill and John Reed. Several of the poems by O'Neill and a short story by Reed seem not to have been published previously. Reed's writings include a scrapbook that contains his notes and clippings relating to his literary writing and rejection letters from literary magazines. The Unidentified manuscripts are writings that cannot be readily identified as the work of Bryant or another author. These manuscripts are organized by the type of writing.
  - Literary
    - Notes (Box 10, Folder 1 - 14)
      General
    - Notes (Box 11, Folder 15 - 18)
    - Plays
      - "The Best Seller", 1926 (Box 11, Folder 19 - 21)
      - "The End of the Candle", undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - "From Paris to Main Street", undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - The Game, 1916 (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - "Patient Griselda", 1919 (Box 11, Folder 25 - 26)
    - Poems, 1914-1934, undated (Box 12, Folder 27 - 37)
    - Short stories
      - "The Autobiography of an Idle Woman", undated (Box 12, Folder 38)
      - "The Blue Danube", undated (Box 12, Folder 39)
      - "The Bride of Death", undated (Box 12, Folder 40)
      - "Charity in Teeth", undated (Box 12, Folder 41)
      - "Fables for Proletarian Children", undated (Box 12, Folder 42)
      - "The Goose and Goldy", undated (Box 12, Folder 43)
      - "Inspiration", undated (Box 12, Folder 44)
      - "Letters from the Dead", undated (Box 12, Folder 45)
      - "The Model", undated (Box 12, Folder 46)
      - "Now I Can Laugh", undated (Box 12, Folder 47)
      - "The Perfect Lady", undated (Box 12, Folder 48)
      - "The Permissionaire", undated (Box 12, Folder 49)
      - "The Prodigal Father", undated (Box 12, Folder 50)
      - "Respectability", undated (Box 12, Folder 51)
      - "Serge", undated (Box 12, Folder 52)
      - "The Sins of the Fathers", undated (Box 12, Folder 53)
      - "St. George and the Great Adventure", undated (Box 12, Folder 54)
      - "Story of the Pregnant Woman and the Boy Who Loved Her", undated (Box 12, Folder 55)
      - "The Strength of Traditions", undated (Box 12, Folder 56)
      - "The Unlit Shrine", undated (Box 12, Folder 57)
      - "The Widow", undated (Box 12, Folder 58)
  - Journalism
    - D'Annunzio articles
      - Notes, [ca. 1923] (Box 13, Folder 59)
      - Research material, [ca. 1923] (Box 13, Folder 60)
    - Draft articles [includes photographs], undated (Box 13, Folder 61 - 66)
    - Draft fragments, undated (Box 13, Folder 67 - 70)
    - International News Service cables, 1920-1923 (Box 14, Folder 71 - 75)
    - "Mirrors of Moscow"
      - Drafts, [ca. 1923] (Box 14, Folder 76 - 79)
      - Galleys, [ca. 1923] (Box 14, Folder 80)
      - "Lenin and His Lieutenants" articles
        - Notes, undated (Box 14, Folder 81 - 82)
        - Research materials, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 83 - 84)
    - Notes (Box 15, Folder 85 - 90)
    - "The Poets' Revolution", 1916 (Box 15, Folder 91)
    - Press credentials, 1917-1926 (Box 15, Folder 92)
    - Six Red Months in Russia
      - Draft fragments, undated (Box 15, Folder 93)
      - Pamphlets, bookjackets, and illustrations, 1918 (Box 15, Folder 94)
    - Unidentified radiograms, 1920-1921 (Box 15, Folder 95)
  - Journals and notebooks
    - Provincetown Players, [ca. 1916] (Box 15, Folder 96)
    - France, 1917 (Box 15, Folder 97)
    - Russia, 1917-1918 (Box 15, Folder 98 - 100)
    - Russia, 1920 (Box 16, Folder 101 - 104)
    - "Trip to Bokhara", 1921 (Box 16, Folder 105)
    - Latvia, 1921 (Box 16, Folder 106 - 107)
    - Turkey, 1923 (Box 16, Folder 108)
    - Unidentified fragments, 1917, undated (Box 16, Folder 109)
      See also: Oversize Folder 2
  - Speeches, 1919 (Box 16, Folder 110)
  - Writings by others
    - O'Neill, Eugene, 1916, undated (Box 16, Folder 111)
    - Reed, John, 1913-1919, undated (Box 16, Folder 112 - 116)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 17, Folder 117 - 118)
  - Unidentified manuscripts
    - Journalism (Box 17, Folder 119)
    - Journalism fragments (Box 17, Folder 120)
    - Literary fragments (Box 17, Folder 121)
    - Plays (Box 17, Folder 122)
    - Poems (Box 17, Folder 123)
    - Political writings (Box 17, Folder 124)
    - Short stories (Box 17, Folder 125)
- Visual Artwork, 1915-1933; Series III
  This series contains drawings, paintings, and sketchbooks. Most of the drawings are of people and a smaller portion are political cartoons. The paintings are mostly watercolors depicting landscapes and objects. Most of the sketchbooks have drawings on only a small number of pages. While some of the artwork is signed by Bryant, much of it is unsigned and therefore might be the work of someone else. Almost all of the artwork is undated.
  - Drawings, 1915-1933, undated (Box 18, Folder 1 - 5)
    See also: Oversize Folder 3
    See also: Oversize Folder 12
  - Paintings, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
    See also: Oversize Folder 4 - 5
  - Sketchbooks, undated (Box 18, Folder 7 - 10)
- Photographs, 1909-1928; Series IV
  This series contains black and white photographic prints and negatives of mixed quality arranged by subject. The photographs document Louise Bryant's travels throughout Europe and the Middle East, much of it relating to her work as a journalist. There are also many photographs of her family and friends and a small number that document her involvement with the Provincetown Players.
  The Russia folders contain an assortment of pictures from her visits to Russia between 1917 and 1922. A substantial proportion of these photographs concern the Bolshevik Revolution of 1917 that Bryant and her second husband John Reed witnessed and reported on for the American press. These pictures include street and crowd scenes, buildings, a few of the leaders of the Provisional Government and the Bolsheviks such as Alexander Kerensky and Leon Trotsky, and other individuals. Some of these have annotations identifying them, mostly written by what appears to be Bryant's hand. Several of the Russia photographs have annotations that indicate they originally belonged to John Reed. Since many of the photographs are not annotated and not readily identifiable, photographs relating to Russia may also be found in other folders such as Other individuals and Boats, waterscapes, and landscapes.
  Many of the photographs document Bryant's travels in Turkey and the Middle East. Subjects include street scenes, buildings, and individuals in Constantinople and Angora (Ankara) and archaelogical sites in Egypt. Some of the photographs are annotated with identifying information, mostly not in Bryant's handwriting. Since many of the photographs are not annotated and not readily identifiable, photographs relating to her Middle East travels may be found in other folders such as Small groups, Art and archaelogical sites, and Other buildings. Some of the photographs may relate to Bryant's 1921 trip to Uzbekistan, but none have been specifically identified as such.
  Several photographs are of theatrical productions of the Provincetown Players for which Bryant wrote and acted. Most depict a staging of Bryant's play The Game, but also included are performances of Floyd Dell's King Arthur's Socks and Eugene O'Neill's Thirst and Bound East for Cardiff. O'Neill is pictured as acting in both of his plays.
  A large portion of the photographs in this series show Bryant, her friends, and family or are otherwise of a personal nature. There are multiple photographs of her second husband John Reed, her daughter Anne Bullitt, her lover Eugene O'Neill, and Refik, a Turkish boy who lived with Bryant and her third husband William C. Bullitt in Paris and became part of the family. Photographs of Bullitt can be found in his papers which are maintained as a separate collection in Manuscripts and Archives at Yale University Library.
  Many of the negatives correspond to the photographic prints contained in this series, but some have no prints in the collection. Some of the negatives seem to be from John Reed's time spent reporting on the Mexican Revolution in 1914 because they depict groups of men, often armed and on horseback, and desert scenes, but these negatives have not been positively identified. These negatives have no photographic copies in the collection. Since most of the negatives are in poor condition, few have been systematically arranged. The greater share of the negatives that duplicate the photographic prints in this series can be found among the miscellaneous negatives.
  - Prints
    - People
      - Bryant, Louise, 1917, undated (Box 19, Folder 1 - 2)
      - Bryant, Louise with others, 1928, undated (Box 19, Folder 3 - 5)
      - Bullitt, Anne, 1925-1926, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Mussolini, Benito, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - O'Neill, Eugene, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Provincetown Players, [ca. 1916] (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Reed, John, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Refik, undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - Viruboff, Alexander, 1922, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - Other individuals, 1918-1921, undated (Box 19, Folder 13 - 15)
      - Other individuals, 1918-1921, undated (Box 20, Folder 16 - 18)
      - Small groups, 1921-1922, undated (Box 20, Folder 19 - 21)
      - Crowds, undated (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Animals and objects, undated (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Art and archaelogical sites, undated (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - Boats, waterscapes, and landscapes, undated (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - Houses, undated (Box 20, Folder 26)
    - Middle East and North Africa, undated (Box 20, Folder 27 - 28)
    - Other buildings, undated (Box 20, Folder 29)
    - Russia, 1917-1922, undated (Box 21, Folder 30 - 32)
    - Turkey, 1921-1926 (Box 21, Folder 33 - 34)
  - Negatives
    - Bryant, Louise, undated (Box 21, Folder 35)
    - "Constantinople, Asiatic side", undated (Box 21, Folder 36)
    - Mexican Revolution [?], undated (Box 21, Folder 37)
    - "Portland, etc.", 1909 (Box 21, Folder 38)
    - Provincetown beach, [ca. 1916] (Box 21, Folder 39)
    - Turkey, undated (Box 21, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous, 1920-1923, undated (Box 21, Folder 41 - 45)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 22, Folder 46 - 54)
- Personal Papers, 1917-1936; Series V
  This series is comprised of legal, financial, and medical documents, address books, membership cards, daily calendars, objects, and notes. Since these notes were intermingled with Bryant's literary and journalism notes when they arrived at Yale, it is possible that a small portion of them might be relevant to Bryant's writings. The legal documents include travel papers, official passes, some of them Russian, a book contract for Six Red Months in Russia, and material related to Bryant's divorce from William C. Bullitt. A small assortment of objects include protest sashes against the blockade of Russia, devotional items, and military insignia.
  - Address books, undated (Box 23, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Anne Bullitt's childhood drawings, undated (Box 23, Folder 3 - 4)
  - Business cards and addresses (Box 23, Folder 5 - 7)
  - Daily calendars, 1921-1922, 1927 (Box 23, Folder 8 - 10)
  - Envelopes, empty (Box 24, Folder 11 - 16)
  - Financial (Box 24, Folder 17 - 21)
  - Financial (Box 25, Folder 22 - 26)
  - French language exercises (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - Legal, 1917-1936 (Box 25, Folder 28 - 29)
  - Medical, 1928, undated (Box 25, Folder 30)
    See also: Oversize Folder 6
  - Membership cards and passes, 1917-1922, undated (Box 25, Folder 31)
  - Notes (Box 25, Folder 32 - 34)
  - Objects, undated (Box 26)
  - Objects, undated (Box 27)
  - Objects, undated (Box 28)
- Printed Matter, 1908-1935; Series VI
  This series is made up of printed and published material collected by Bryant. It includes pamphlets, magazines, journals, press clippings, postcards, and other matter. It is arranged by type of material with the exception of two small subject files on Irish independence and the Provincetown Players. Material relating to revolutionary Russia can be found under Clippings, Pamphlets, and Miscellaneous in addition to the headings beginning with "Russian." The Clippings files contain copies of articles by and about Bryant and John Reed as well as articles on the Russian Revolution and various other topics.
  - Art prints, undated (Box 29, Folder 1)
    See also: Oversize Folder 7
  - The Bullitt Mission to Russia [inscribed by Bryant], 1919
  - Clippings
    - Book reviews (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 29, Folder 3 - 15)
      See also: Oversize Folder 13
    - Miscellaneous (Box 30, Folder 16 - 31)
  - Ephemera (Box 31, Folder 32)
  - Handbills, miscellaneous, 1919, undated (Box 31, Folder 33)
  - Irish independence, 1922-1923 (Box 31, Folder 34)
  - Journals and magazines
    - Asia, 1925 (Box 31, Folder 35)
    - Liberator, 1918-1921 (Box 31, Folder 36 - 42)
    - Nation, 1921-1926 (Box 31, Folder 43)
    - Poetry, 1920-1925 (Box 31, Folder 44)
    - Poetry, 1928-1930 (Box 32, Folder 45 - 46)
    - Soviet Russia, 1919-1921 (Box 32, Folder 47 - 48)
    - Miscellaneous, 1918-1935 (Box 32, Folder 49 - 51)
      See also: Oversize Folder 8
  - Maps and blueprints, undated (Box 32, Folder 52)
    See also: Oversize Folder 14
  - Memorabilia (Box 32, Folder 53 - 54)
  - Pamphlets
    - Political, 1910-1927, undated (Box 32, Folder 55 - 56)
    - Russian, 1917-1921, undated (Box 33, Folder 57 - 58)
    - Miscellaneous, 1908-1929, undated (Box 33, Folder 59 - 63)
  - Plays and librettos, 1917-1918, undated (Box 33, Folder 64 - 66)
  - Postcards, blank, undated (Box 33, Folder 67 - 68)
  - Postcards, blank, undated (Box 34, Folder 69 - 74)
  - Provincetown Players, [1916] (Box 34, Folder 75)
    See also: Oversize Folder 15
  - Russian children's book, undated (Box 34, Folder 76)
  - Russian handbills, 1918, undated (Box 34, Folder 77)
  - Russian posters, 1917 (Box 34, Folder 78)
    See also: Oversize Folder 10
  - Songs and sheet music, 1919, undated (Box 34, Folder 79)
    See also: Oversize Folder 11
  - Miscellaneous, 1915-1933 (Box 34, Folder 80)
- Oversize
  - Correspondence, poems, and writing notes, undated (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified radiograms, undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Paintings, undated (Box 35, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Medical x-ray, 1927 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Art prints, undated (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Journals and magazines, 1916-1918, 1927 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlets, undated (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Russian poster, 1917 (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Songs and sheet music, 1912, 1920-1921, undated (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Drawings, 1926, undated (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1923 (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - Maps and blueprints, undated (Box 36, Folder 14)
  - Provincetown Players, [1916] (Box 36, Folder 15)
- Additional material, 1916-1928; Accession 2008-M-036
  - Books
    - Baring, Maurice. A Year in Russia. (Methuen & Co., 1917). "John Reed / Petrograd / Nov. 1917" written on inside cover; William. C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Benson, Allan L. Inviting War to America. (B.W. Huebsch, 1916). "Reed" written inside (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bourdet, Edouard. The Captive. (Brentano's, 1926). "Louise Bryant" written inside (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Brissenden, Paul F. The I. W. W.: A Study of American Syndicalism. (Columbia University, 1919). "John Reed" written inside; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bryant, Louise. Mirrors of Moscow (Thomas Seltzer, 1923) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Claudel, Paul. The East I Know. (Yale University Press, 1914). Presentation inscription to John Reed from V. L. W.; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Garnett, David. Go She Must! (Alfred A. Knopf, 1927). "Louise Bryant" written inside (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Glasgow, Ellen. The Romantic Comedians. (Doubleday, Page & Co., 1926). "Louise Bryant" written on illustrated lining paper and "Bryant Bullitt" written on title page (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Harris, Frank. Oscar Wilde: His Life and Confessions, Volume 1. (Self-published, 1918). Presentation inscription to Louise Bryant by the author, April 1918; William C. Bullitt bookplate; includes TLS, 1918 May 2, from Harris to Bryant (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lee, Vernon. Pope Jacynth: To Which Are Added Ariadne in Mantua and Other Romantic Inventions. (Bernhard Tauchnitz, 1906). "This book belongs to Louise Bryant, 84 rue d'Assas, Paris, France" written inside in her hand (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lippmann, Walter. Drift and Mystery: An Attempt to Diagnose the Current Unrest. (Mitchell Kennerley, 1914). "Reed" written inside; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - McCoy, Samuel. Merchants of the Morning. (George H. Doran, 1919). Presentation inscription to John Reed by the author, October, 1919; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - McKay, Claude
      - Harlem Shadows: The Poems of Claude McKay. (Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1922). Presentation inscription to Louise Bryant from the author, New Year, 1924; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Home to Harlem. (Harper & Brothers, 1928). Published dedication: "To my friend Louise Bryant;" William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Masses. Bound, Volume IX, no. 3 (Issue 67, 1917 Jan)-Volume X, no. 1 and 2 (Issue 77-78, 1917 Nov-Dec) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Merriman, Brian. The Midnight Court and the Adventures of a Luckless Fellow. (Boni and Liveright, [1926]). Louise Bryant written on inside cover (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Morton, J. B. The Adventures of Mr. Thake. (Jonathan Cape, 1934). Presentation inscription to Louise Bryant by Mina, Dublin, 1934; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Norton, Allen. Saloon Sonnets: With Sunday Flutings. (Claire Marie, 1914). Presentation inscription to Louise Bryant by the author; William C. Bullitt bookplate; includes two undated notes from Norton to Bryant (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Reed, John. Ten Days That Shook the World. (Boni & Liveright, 1922). Includes clipping Reed's grave in the Kremlin (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Roth, Samuel. Europe: A Book for America. (Boni and Liveright, 1919). Presentation inscription to Louise Bryant by Allen Norton; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sheean, Vincent. An American Among the Riffi. (The Century Co., 1926). Presentation inscription to Louise Bryant by the author (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Sinclair, Upton. The Profits of Religion: An Essay in Economic Interpretation. (Self-published, 1918). Presentation inscription on cover to John Reed by the author (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Strindberg, August. On the Seaboard: A Novel of the Baltic Islands. (Stewart & Kidd Company, 1913). Louise Bryant written inside. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Towne, Charles Hanson. Youth and Other Poems. (Mitchell Kennerly, 1911). Presentation inscription to John Reed by the author, Spring 1912; manuscript poem written on inside front cover by Reed, 1912 May 17; William C. Bullitt bookplate (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Van Loon, Hendrik. The Story of Wilbur the Hat: Being a True Account of the Strange Things Which Sometimes Happen in a Part of the World Which Does Not Exist / Written and Drawn for the Fun of It by Hendrik Willem van Loon and Published as Usual by Horace B. Liveright of 61 West 48 Street, New York City; Passed by the Westport Board of Censors, Eleanor Brooks, Pres. Presentation inscription to Louise Bryant by the author, 1925 Mar 7. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Letters inserted in books by Harris (1918 May 2) and Norton (undated), circa 1914-1918 (Box 3, Folder 26)